A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ), Governance and Civil Society, Office Files of Urvashi Vaid FA667
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ), Governance and Civil Society, Office Files of Urvashi Vaid
1992-2005
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA667
2.4 Cubic Feet
The Office Files of Urvashi Vaid, Deputy Director of the Ford Foundation’s Governance and Civil Society (GCS) unit from 2001-2005, document her oversight of grants to support citizens’ groups working for social and economic justice, to strengthen civil society organizations and to improve government performance. The bulk of the records pertain to the Collaborations that Count Initiative. The collection spans the years 1992-2005 and consists of correspondence, memoranda, reports, grant proposals, meeting materials and publications. There are substantial records that document grant work prior to Vaid’s tenure, including files created by former GCS staff members Michael Lipsky and June Zeitlin, and GCS Director Michael Edwards. The files were transferred to the Ford Foundation Archives in August 2005. The arrangement of the collection follows the original order maintained by Vaid, though a few unfoldered and stray items have been interfiled by the processing archivist.
Conditions Governing Access
Material more than ten years old is open for scholarly research.
Select individual files are restricted, as noted. Permission to access these files must be obtained from the Ford Foundation before scholarly access is permitted.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in the following series and subseries:
Series I. Collaborations That Count, 1998-2005
Subseries A. State Collaborations, 1998-2005 Grant proposals, grantee reports, correspondence, memoranda, publications and other materials documenting activities funded by the Ford Foundation in the eleven states targeted by the initiative. Files are arranged alphabetically by state name.
Subseries B. Ancillary Organizations, 1998-2003 In addition to providing direct funding for eleven state-based collaborations, the Ford Foundation gave over $5.2 million to organizations that provided technical assistance, research, training and other services to the project. Files pertaining to these grants contain memoranda, correspondence and reports and are arranged alphabetically by organization name.
Subseries C. Administration and Evaluation, 1998-2004 Subseries includes project planning memos and reports, requests for proposals, regional meeting agendas and materials, publicity material, evaluation planning proposals and a copy of the final project evaluation, “Power, Participation and State-based Politics” (2004). Files are arranged alphabetically by subject.
Series II. Subjects, 1992-2005 Records concerning a variety of Ford Foundation activities, including grant initiatives, conferences, program officer meetings and Trustee trips. There is a substantial file containing memos and correspondence pertaining to the State Fiscal Analysis Initiative. Several folders document meetings of program officers from the Civil Society unit with staff from other program areas to discuss shared strategies and themes for grantmaking (Box 2, Folders 18, 19, 22). There are also briefing books and related materials pertaining to trips to Alabama and China by Ford Foundation Trustees who served on the Peace and Social Justice Committee. The files are arranged alphabetically by subject.
Scope and Contents
The Office Files of Urvashi Vaid document grant-making by the Ford Foundation’s Governance and Civil Society and Governance and Public Policy programs during the period 1992-2005. The collection measures two linear feet and is contained in two record cartons. The bulk of the records relate to the Collaborations that Count project, 1998-2004. The files contain correspondence, memoranda, reports, grant proposals and meeting materials. There are substantial records that document grant work prior to Vaid’s tenure, including files created by former GCS staff members Michael Lipsky and June Zeitlin, and GCS Director Michael Edwards.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be restricted from scholarly research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment.
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be restricted from scholarly research at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/RAC Head of Reference.
Biographical / Historical
Social activist, attorney and foundation executive Urvashi Vaid was born in India in 1958 and moved to the United States when she was eight years old. She became politically active at age eleven by participating in marches protesting the U.S. war against Vietnam. Vaid attended Vassar College on an academic scholarship and graduated in 1979 with a bachelor's degree in English and political science. She then spent three months as a volunteer intern with the Women's Prison Project and worked as a legal secretary and administrative assistant for a Boston law firm. During the early 1980s, Vaid helped found the Boston Lesbian/Gay Political Alliance and the Allston-Brighton Greenlight Safehouse Network, an anti-violence neighborhood project. Vaid attended the Northeastern University School of Law, and received a J.D. degree in 1983. From 1983-1986, Vaid worked for the American Civil Liberties Union's National Prisons Project, where she conducted class action lawsuits to improve conditions in American prisons. She then joined the staff of the National Gay and Lesbian Task Force, serving as Media Director (1986-1989), Executive Director (1989-1992), and Policy Institute Director (1997-2000).
Vaid joined the Ford Foundation in 2000 as a Program Officer, and in January 2001 was appointed Deputy Director of the Governance and Civil Society program. A major emphasis of her work was the Collaborations that Count initiative, which was launched in 1998 to support cooperation among state-level organizations working for social and economic justice. Vaid also played a role in the State Fiscal Analysis Initiative, and oversaw grants to support gay, lesbian, bisexual and transgender rights organizations. Vaid left the Ford Foundation in 2005 to head the Arcus Foundation.
Vaid is author of Virtual Equality: The Mainstreaming of Gay & Lesbian Liberation (Anchor, 1996), and is co-editor, with John D’Emilio and William Turner, of Creating Change: Public Policy, Sexuality and Civil Rights (St. Martin's Press, 2000).
The Governance and Civil Society unit was established as part of a significant reorganization of the Ford Foundation during 1996-1997. The program incorporated much of the work and staff of the former Governance and Public Policy unit, and at its inception aimed “to improve governmental performance and accountability, stimulate new approaches to designing and implementing public policies, and enhance the role of civic organizations, particularly philanthropies, in promoting democratic values.” (Ford Foundation Annual Report, 1996)
Collaborations that Count, originally known as the “Devolution Initiative,” was launched by GCS in 1998. During the mid-1990s federal funds and decision-making power for many U.S. government social programs were transferred to the state and local level. To succeed in this new political environment, state-based public policy and civil society groups needed to develop new leadership skills, broaden membership, enhance organizational infrastructures and work together more effectively. Towards these ends, Collaborations that Count provided over $18 million in funds to support cooperative projects in Alabama, Idaho, Kentucky, Mississippi, Nevada, North Carolina, Oregon, South Carolina, Tennessee, Texas and Washington. Public policy and social issue groups in these states formed new coalitions that organized conferences and workshops, developed staff training programs, improved technology access, commissioned research and reached out to the public. Specific issues addressed by collaborators included welfare and tax reform, immigrant rights, healthcare access, affordable housing and racial justice. Significant policy outcomes linked to the work of Collaborations that Count-supported groups included minimum wage and labor contract reforms (Idaho), food stamp reform (Oregon) and increased funding for education (Mississippi).
In her role as Deputy Director for Ford Foundation GCS work, Urvashi Vaid coordinated Collaborations that Count during 2001-2004.
Related Materials
FA592 Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice (PSJ), Governance and Civil Society, Deputy Director, Office Files of Urvashi Vaid, 1982-2005.
Ford Foundation
- Collaborations that Count, 1998-2005; I
  Conditions Governing Access
  Records in this series span the dates 1998-2005. Records less than 10 years old will be open to research once they reach the ten year threshold, 2016.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged into 3 subseries.
  - State Collaborations, 1998-2005; A
    Files are arranged alphabetically by state name.
    Scope and Contents
    Grant proposals, grantee reports, correspondence, memoranda, publications and other materials documenting activities funded by the Ford Foundation in the eleven states targeted by the initiative.
    - Alabama: Alabama Organizing Project, 1999 - 2001 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Idaho: The Idaho Collaborative, 1998 - 2002 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Kentucky: Kentucky Economic Justice Alliance, 1998 - 2004 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Mississippi: Mississippi Education Working Group – Southern Echo, Inc., 1998 - 2003 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Nevada: Progressive Leadership Alliance of Nevada, 1998 - 2005 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Some of the records in this file are restricted because they are less than 10 years old. The restricted items have been segregated and are inaccessible. The file is open to research, and physical removal of the segregated material is not necessary.
      Date Restricted Material -- Contains records less than 10 years old -- Restricted records are Open to scholarly research in 2016.
    - North Carolina: North Carolina Alliance for Economic Justice, 1998 - 2002 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Oregon: The Oregon Collaborative – Rural Organizing Project, 1998 - 2002 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - South Carolina: South Carolina Policy and Organizing Project – Carolina Alliance for Fair Employment (CAFE), 1998 - 2003 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Tennessee: Tennessee Partnership on Organizing and Public Policy – Save Our Cumberland Mountains, 1998 - 2002 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Texas: ProTex: Network for a Progressive Texas, 1998 - 2002 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Washington: Washington Living Wage Movement – Washington Association of Churches, 1998 - 2005 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Ancillary Organizations, 1998-2003; B
    Arranged alphabetically by organization name.
    In addition to providing direct funding for eleven state-based collaborations, the Ford Foundation gave over $5.2 million to organizations that provided technical assistance, research, training and other services to the project. Files pertaining to these grants contain memoranda, correspondence and reports.
    - Alliance for Justice, 1998 - 2002 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Community Resource Exchange, 2001 - 2002 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Creative Communications, 1998 - 2000 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Education Resources Group, 1999 - 2000 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - John J. Koprowski & Associates, Inc., 1999 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Northwest Federation of Community Organizations, 2002 - 2003 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Progressive Technology Project, 1999 - 2000 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Southern Partners Fund, 2000 - 2001 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Western States Center, 1999-2001 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Administration and Evaluation, 1998-2004; C
    Subseries includes project planning memos and reports, requests for proposals, regional meeting agendas and materials, publicity material, evaluation planning proposals and a copy of the final project evaluation, “Power, Participation and State-based Politics” (2004) (which remains closed from scholarly research until 2015).
    Files are arranged alphabetically by subject.
    - Devolution Initiative, 1998 - 1999 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Devolution Team Binder, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Evaluation briefing, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Evaluation report – Applied Research Center. “Power, Participation and State-based Politics", 2004 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Evaluation proposals, 2001 - 2004 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Foundation Administered Project (FAP) grant, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Initiative Statement, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - National Meeting, 1998, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
    - Northwest Regional Meeting, 2000 - 2001 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Publicity material, 1998 - 2000 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Request for proposals, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Southern Regional Meeting, 2001 - 2002 (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
    - Web site, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Work plans, 2000 - 2001 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Subjects, 1992-2005; II
  Records in this series span the dates 1992-2005. Records less than 10 years old will be open to research once they reach the ten year threshold, 2016.
  Records concerning a variety of Ford Foundation activities, including grant initiatives, conferences, program officer meetings and Trustee trips. There is a substantial file containing memos and correspondence pertaining to the State Fiscal Analysis Initiative. Several folders document meetings of program officers from the Civil Society unit with staff from other program areas to discuss shared strategies and themes for grantmaking (Box 2, Folders 18, 19, 22). There are also briefing books and related materials pertaining to trips to Alabama and China by Ford Foundation Trustees who served on the Peace and Social Justice Committee.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Campus Compact National Student Summit, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Civil Society and Community Development meeting, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Civil Society and Social Justice meeting, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Conference on Diversity and Coexistence in Asia, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Convening on GLBT Rights and Issues and Religious Traditions in the US: Framing Difficult Dialogues and Seeking New Partnerships, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Governance and Civil Society meeting, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Non-profit Infrastructure Funders Group, 2002 - 2005 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Peace and Social Justice accomplishments, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Peace and Social Justice Trustee Committee Spring Trip to Alabama, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Peace and Social Justice Trustee Committee Spring Trip to China, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Post 9/11 September 11, 2001 grants, 2001 - 2003 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Program Division Joint Worldwide Meting, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Replenishing Democracy Initiative, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Social movements, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - State Fiscal Analysis Initiative, 1992 - 2004 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Appendix A: Reports Removed
  Separated Materials
  The following list of Unpublished Reports written by Ford Foundation staff and consultants were removed from the office files of Urvashi Vaid, and transferred to the Ford Foundation Archive’s Unpublished Reports collection of staff and consultant reports. The reports are listed in alphabetical order by author.
  - Applied Research Center. Power, Participation, & State-Based Politics: An Evaluation of the Ford Foundation’s Collaborations that Count Initiative., 2004 (Report 16348)
  - Clark, Terry A. and Adamson, Rebecca. Linkages Among Policy and Organizing Groups in the Devolution Initiative’s Collaborations that Count, 1998-2000., 2001 (Report 16647)
  - Ford Foundation. Briefing Book: Civil Society and Community Development meeting briefing book, February 23-25, 2002, Pocantico-Tarrytown NY. (Report 16646)
  - Ford Foundation. Briefing Book: Governance and Civil Society meeting, February 23-25, 2002, Pocantico-Tarrytown NY. (Report 16642)
  - Ford Foundation. Briefing Book: PSJ Trustee Committee Spring Trip to Alabama, March 25-28, 2002. (Report 16644)
  - Ford Foundation. Briefing Book: PSJ Trustee Committee Spring Trip to China, March 22-27, 2004. (Report 16643)
  - Matakis, Brian. The State Fiscal Analysis Initiative: A Summary Report to The Charles Stewart Mott Foundation June 10-11 Meeting., 1998 (Report 16645)